HASHAN DANANJAYA FERNANDO

DATA SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING GRADUATE STUDENT UNIVERSITY OF TENNESSEE, KNOXVILLE

To enhance the knowledge in Data Science and effectively utilize it for research and development.

PERSONAL PROFILE

I am a graduate student with a strong background in Statistics, Operations Research, and Computer Science, with a focus on Data Science, Epidemiology, and Big Data. As a proactive and creative researcher, I am passionate about applying advanced methodologies such as Topological Data Analysis and Machine Learning to tackle complex public health challenges.

EDUCATION

OBJECTIVE

DATA SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING PHD | READING

The Bredesen Center, The University of Tennessee, Knoxville, United States Current GPA: 4.00/4.00

MASTER OF SCIENCE (M.SC.) IN DATA SCIENCE

Postgraduate Institute of Science, University of Peradeniya, Sri Lanka Final GPA: 3.75/4.00 (Merit Scholarship Awarded)

B.SC. IN STATISTICS AND OPERATIONS RESEARCH

Faculty of Science, University of Peradeniya, Sri Lanka Subjects: Statistics, Computer Science, and Mathematics Final GPA: 3.06/4.00

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

PhD Research - Geospatial Study of Opioid Overdose Risk in USA

I am currently engaged in research focused on leveraging advanced Machine Learning techniques and Topological Data Analysis to predict opioid overdose risk across various regions in the United States. In addition, I am developing new spatial-temporal methodologies to more accurately identify future high-risk areas.

• AHEAD Innovation Commercialization Enhancement grants - "Tampering and Sound Based IoT Framework for Real-Time Thermo-Mechanically Treated Steel Cargo Theft Detection"

In this study, machine learning techniques and low powered IoT devices were used to identify real-time theft detection.

Smart Seal

Developed a smart seal using ESP8266 for steel-based cargo protection. This device is almost ready to commercialize.

Audio Detection System
 The audio detection system detects the theft with the help of Raspberry Pi and convolution neural networks (CNN).

PERSONAL INFORMATION

Nationality

Sri Lankan

Phone

(+1)8653215237

Email

hfernand@vols.utk.edu

LinkedIn

https://www.linkedin.com/in/hashandananjaya1/

GitHub

https://github.com/hashansl

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming Languages

C, Java, Python, R

Libraries

Keras, Tensorflow, PyTorch, Numpy, Scipy, Scikit-learn

Technology Stack

RStudio, MINITAB, SPSS, Weka, Google Cloud IoT, Arduino, Raspberry Pi technologies

PROFESSIONAL APPOINTMENTS

- Working as a Research Assistant in the Oak Ridge National Laboratory, Tennessee,
 United States. (2022 to present)
- Worked as a Research Assistant in the Faculty of Science, University of Peradeniya,
 Sri Lanka. (December 2019 to 2022)
- Worked as a Data Scientist (Intern) in VizuaMatix, Nawala, Sri Lanka. (January 2019 to December 2019)
- Worked as a Planning Intern in MAS Active Linea Intimo, Biyagama, Sri Lanka.
 (October 2018 to January 2019)

PRESENTATIONS

- A Geospatial Study of Opioid Overdose Risk in Washington D.C Metropolitan Area Interdisciplinary Association for Population Health Science 2024 (St. Louis)
- A Geospatial Study of Opioid Overdose Risk in Diverse Regions
 International Population Data Linkage Network Conference 2024 (Chicago)

PROJECTS

- "Intelligent Transportation through the Integration of IoT" by AHEAD Innovation
 Commercialization Enhancement grants Developed smart theft detecting device using
 Internet of Things and Machine Learning.
- MSc Independent Study Automatic Bird Sound Identification using Machine Learning.
- VizuaMatix Developed a Machine learning model to predict non-performing customers in a banking system. Purpose was to accurately classify the banking loans into performing and non-performing customers.
- Noritake Lanka Porcelain Developed an Inventory management model for raw materials at Noritake Lanka Porcelain. Purpose was to minimize the inventory cost for raw materials.
- MAS Active Linea Intimo Developed several useful VBA applications for the internal use.

EXTRACURRICULAR ACTIVITIES

- University colors for cricket from The University of Peradeniya (2016/2017/2018)
- Member of Statistics and Operations Research Society, University of Peradeniya
- \bullet Represented U13, U15 and U17 cricket teams in Christ Church College, Matale

REFEREES

Dr. Adam Spannaus

Research Scientist,

Advanced Computing for Health Sciences section,

Oak Ridge National Laboratory,

(+1) 8653123316

spannausat@ornl.gov

Mr. Prabhath Gunathilake

 $Senior\,Lecturer\,in\,Computer\,Science\,Department\,of\,Statistics\,and\,Computer\,Science,$

Faculty of Science,

University of Peradeniya.

(+94) 77 741 0161

prabhath@pdn.ac.lk

I do hereby certify that the above particulars mentioned by me are true and correct to the best of my knowledge.

H.D. Fernando